{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A rebellion against this man occurred because Emma's marriage to Ralph de Gaël was not sanctioned. That revolt against this man is known as the Revolt of the Earls. This man ordered allegiance in the Salisbury Oath, and at the southern end of the London Bridge, this man fought Ansgar [[ON-sgar]] the Staller and burned Southwark [[SUH-therk]]. This man built the White Tower, created the New Forest for royal hunting, and commissioned the Domesday [[DOOMS-day]] Book for listing landholdings. For ten points, name this Norman King who won at Hastings.",
      "answer": [
        "William the Conqueror",
        "William I",
        "William the Bastard"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2010, various artists proclaimed \"[Do this action] Day\" after Episode 201 of South Park was censored on Comedy Central. In 2015, Elton Simpson, along with an accomplice, attacked the Curtis Culwell Center, because the American Freedom Defense Initiative, or AFDI, did this. The AFDI had held the event because earlier that year, militants slaughtered artists at Charlie Hebdo who had done, for ten points, what haram action relating to the last prophet of Islam?",
      "answer": "Depicting Muhammad"
    },
    {
      "question": "A man in this position, Newton Baker, rejected David Lloyd George’s advice on how to mobilize a nation. Robert Todd Lincoln served in this position during the James Garfield and Chester Arthur administrations, putting down the Cincinnati Riots of 1884. Andrew Johnson violated the Tenure of Office Act by sacking a man in this position, leading to his impeachment. For ten points, name this Cabinet position held by Jefferson Davis and Edwin Stanton, now known as the Secretary of Defense.",
      "answer": "United States Secretary of War"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a rookie, this Hall-of-Famer batted .174 [[One seventy-four]] for Kansas City. Five years later, this man won his first of three World Series in a row and was voted league MVP the following year. A teammate described this flamboyant player saying, \"There isn't enough mustard in the whole world to cover that hotdog.\" When this man retired in 1987, his 563 career home runs ranked him sixth all-time. Holding the World Series records for most runs and most homers in a single series, for ten points, who is this slugger, nicknamed “Mr. October\"?",
      "answer": "Reggie Jackson 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "A battle for power in this country was fought between The Four Musketeers and the Promoters. Phibun [[PEE-BOON]], a member of the Khana Ratsadon People's party, led this country's Rebellion of 18 Corpses. The Black May protests in this country occurred after the NPKC launched a coup. Since 1932, this country has had twenty constitutions, and protestors in this country's Thammasat [[TAH-meh-sawt]] University were attacked in 1973. Ruled by the House of Chakri and kings named Rama, for ten points, name this country once called Siam.",
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Thailand",
        "Siam before \"Black May\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first provisional governor of this state, Wyandot [[WHY-an-dot]] leader William Walker, was unrecognized by the federal government. The first official governor of this state, David Butler, was impeached, and another governor, Silas Holcomb, ran on a combined Democratic/Populist ticket. William Jennings Bryan's brother, Charles Wayland, served as governor of this state, whose first female governor was Kay Orr. In 2015, Pete Ricketts became governor of, for ten points, what state which is governed from Lincoln?",
      "answer": "Nebraska"
    },
    {
      "question": "This proto-state intentionally opened the Nuaimiya Dam near Fallujah to deprive the Shia majority population of water. Late 2016 campaigns led to the loss of this organization’s stronghold of Mosul and its capital of Raqqa [[ROK-ah]]. Donald Trump approved of Operation Kayla Mueller, which killed this leader’s “Caliph” Abu Bakr Al- Baghdadi. For ten points, name this terrorist state which controlled portions of Iraq and Syria.",
      "answer": [
        "Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant",
        "ISIL",
        "Islamic State of Iraq and Syria",
        "ISIS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Shostakovich's Opus 77 is a notable concerto for this instrument in A-minor. The Spanish virtuoso Pablo de Sarasate [[SAR-ah-SAH-tay]] refused to play this instrument for the debut of Brahms's D-major concerto for this instrument due to the length of the oboe section. Vivaldi's Four Seasons are concertos for this instrument, versions of which, including the \"Molitor\" and the \"Lady Blunt,\" were manufactured by Antonio Stradivari. For ten points, name this string instrument played with a bow, which has a higher pitch than a cello or viola.",
      "answer": "Violin or fiddle"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most easterly of these cities, known as eskhata, was founded in the Fergana Valley as a way to maintain contact with the Sogdians. Another of these cities, partially named for a horse, served as a settlement for Iranian and Greek veterans. Another city with this name was the site of the Pharos which was built by the Ptolemies. For ten points, give this shared name of twenty cities founded by Alexander the Great, the most notable containing an extensive library.",
      "answer": "Alexandria"
    },
    {
      "question": "David Koch [[KOHK]] ran on this party’s ticket in the Election of 1980, being the only ticket to platform equality for LGBT individuals in America. It’s not the Republican Party, but one faithless elector voted for a member of this party named Ron Paul in the Election of 2016. The response “What is Aleppo?” was said by a presidential candidate from this party, Gary Johnson. For ten points, name this U.S. party which supports Laissez-faire economics and hands-off government.",
      "answer": "Libertarian Party"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This program was allegorized as Fascism by Kurt Weill [[VILE]] and Maxwell Anderson in Knickerbocker Holiday. Democrat Jouett Shouse [[JO-ett SHOUSS]] opposed this program which was attacked by the American Liberty League, including Empire State Building creator John J. Raskob and the du Pont brothers. This program created the FDIC and allowed for farmers to have electricity in the Rural Electrification Act. The TVA was created under, for ten points, what set of FDR-created programs which aided Americans in the Great Depression?",
        "answer": "The New Deal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Knickerbocker Holiday was based on stories which took place in New Netherland written by this New York writer who went by the pseudonym \"Diedrich Knickerbocker\" and wrote works including \"Rip Van Winkle.\"",
        "answer": "Washington Irving"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist's home was the Down House, whose grounds contain a \"sandwalk\" which this scientist called his \"thinking path.\" On one journey to South America, this scientist wrote that a native species of fox \"would undermine the stability of species.\" This scientist's observations of tortoises helped him formulate his idea that species change over time. This scientist recorded his travels in the book The Voyage of the Beagle. For ten points, name this English scientist, who outlined his theory of natural selection in On the Origin of Species.",
        "answer": "Charles Darwin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "English biologist Thomas Huxley became known by the canine nickname \"Darwin's [this animal]\" following a famous debate with William Wilberforce on the factuality of evolution.",
        "answer": "Bulldog 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1305, a queen of Navarre with this first name supposedly died from witchcraft performed by the Bishop of Troyes [[TWAH]]. Many historical female aristocrats held this name, including \"of Lancaster\" and \"of the Tower.\" A Medieval chronicle written by Jean de Mailly [[mai-YEE]] tells of a female Pope by this name, now widely considered to be fictional. For ten points, give this name commonly associated with a French warrior saint who broke the English and Burgundian siege of Orléans during the Hundred Years' War.",
        "answer": [
          "Joan",
          "Joan I of Navarre",
          "Joan of Lancaster",
          "Joan of the Tower",
          "Pope Joan",
          "Joan of Arc"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Joan of Lancaster, a great-granddaughter of Louis VIII of France and Henry III of England, was a member of the House of Lancaster, a cadet branch of this royal house alongside the House of York.",
        "answer": "Plantagenet"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At McGill, this man won several Wicksteed medals for gymnastics. Luther Gullick may have ordered this man to create a game, but Lambert Will's family disputes that. Legendary coach \"Phog\" Allen was himself coached by this man, who worked to get African- Americans the right to use university swimming pools. Neither dribbling nor free throws were part of this man's original rules. This Canadian invented a sport at the YMCA in Springfield, Massachusetts. For ten points, name this creator of the game of basketball.",
        "answer": "James Naismith"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Naismith spent ten years coaching basketball at this midwestern university, which won National Championships in 1952 under Phog Allen, in 1988 under Larry Brown, and in 2008 under Bill Self.",
        "answer": "University of Kansas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After the 1960 Sharpeville massacre, this organization established the uMkhonto we Sizwe [[oom-KOHN-toh weh SEEZ-weh]], or \"Spear of the Nation.\" The Spear of the Nation was founded by a man who gave his “I Am Prepared to Die” speech at the Rivonia Trial, which sent members of this organization to a prison on Robben Island. This organization elected Cyril Ramaphosa as president in 2017, the year before he was also elected president of South Africa. For ten points, name this South African political party once led by Nelson Mandela.",
        "answer": [
          "African National Congress",
          "ANC"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cyril Ramaphosa served as secretary general to Nelson Mandela and deputy president to this former South African president who resigned in 2018 after a parliamentary vote of no confidence.",
        "answer": [
          "Jacob Zuma",
          "Msholozi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, Gail Halvorsen popularized the mass distribution of candy to children in Operation Little Vittles. SPD party member Ernst Reuter gave a speech beside the ruined Reichstag urging the people of America, England, and France to not abandon his city during this event. At the height of this event, an Allied aircraft reached its target with supplies every thirty seconds. For ten points, name this event in which the Soviets attempted to stop supply lines to the West German capital, the first major crisis of the Cold War.",
        "answer": [
          "Berlin Blockade",
          "Berlin Airlift",
          "or Berliner Luftbrücke"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The catalyst for the Berlin Blockade was the Allied introduction of this new currency, the replacement for the similarly named Reichsmark, to the Soviet sector of Berlin.",
        "answer": "Deutsche Mark"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While traveling on this body of water, one god turned into a blazing disk which blinded an enemy army. Ancient people believed this body of water was controlled from beneath Elephantine Island. This body of water was ruled by gods such as Khnum and the androgynous potbellied deity Hapi. The flooding of this body of water was critical to regional agriculture and was believed to be controlled by the Pharaoh. For ten points, name this river which features prominently in Egyptian mythology.",
        "answer": "Nile River"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to legend, Claudia Quinta once pulled a statue of Cybele [[SIB-uh-lee]] up this other oft-mythologized river. Horatius Cocles [[KOK-lees]] legendarily prayed to this river while defending the Pons Sublicius [[soo-BLIH-see-us]] along its banks.",
        "answer": "Tiber River or Tevere"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the Federal Baseball Club case, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr. stated that this law did not apply to Major League Baseball. It has been argued that this law’s namesake used it to lessen the blow of his ally William McKinley’s harsh tariff passed three months later. This law, strengthened by a 1914 act sponsored by Alabama Representative Henry D. Clayton, was ironically often used to break up labor unions in the late 19th century. For ten points, name this 1890 law intended to limit monopolies.",
        "answer": "Sherman Antitrust Act of 1890"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 1948 Federal court case against this production studio, whose logo includes a lone mountain, changed the way film distribution worked in the U.S. after the studio was found in violation of the Sherman Antitrust Act.",
        "answer": "Paramount Pictures Corporation 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Famous Native Americans",
      "prompt": "Name the Native American, First Nations, or Aboriginal leader who was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Daughter of Powhatan, also named Rebecca Rolfe and Matoaka",
          "answer": "Pocahontas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last member of the Patuxet who taught farming to the Pilgrims in New England",
          "answer": [
            "Squanto",
            "Tisquantum"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Creator of the Cherokee Syllabary who was also known as George Guess",
          "answer": "Sequoyah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Apache medicine man who broke out of a reservation and was exiled to Florida",
          "answer": [
            "Geronimo",
            "Goyaale"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Metis leader and founder of Manitoba who led the Red River Rebellion",
          "answer": "Louis Riel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mohawk leader who founded the Iroquois with Deganawidah",
          "answer": "Hiawatha or Ayenwathaaa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Yamacraw Creek chief who granted land to James Oglethorpe in Georgia",
          "answer": "Tomochichi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last member of the Californian Yahi people whose real name is unknown",
          "answer": "Ishi 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3 The Assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding the assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the assassination of archduke franz ferdinand, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Destructive global conflict which began as a result of the assassination",
          "answer": [
            "World War One or First World War",
            "The Great War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dual monarchy Franz Ferdinand helped lead as Archduke",
          "answer": "Austria-Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who shot Franz Ferdinand after his driver made a wrong turn",
          "answer": "Gavrilo Princip"
        },
        {
          "question": "Serbian nationalist organization that was implicated in the assassination",
          "answer": [
            "The Black Hand",
            "Unification",
            "Death"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Crisis sparked by the assassination during which Russia mobilized its armed forces",
          "answer": "July Crisis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor who, despite hearing of the assassination, continued his spa vacation",
          "answer": "Franz Joseph I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of the archduke who was assassinated along with him",
          "answer": [
            "Sophie, Duchess of Hohenberg",
            "Sophie Chotek"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Crown Prince whose suicide in the Mayerling incident made Franz Ferdinand the heir apparent",
          "answer": "Rudolf 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Han Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country the Han dynasty controlled from Chang'an and later Luoyang",
          "answer": [
            "China",
            "Zhongguo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion legendarily founded by Lao Tsu whose members revolted during the Han",
          "answer": [
            "Taoism or Daoism",
            "or Daojiao"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellion led by Zhang Jiao and named for colorful headwear which weakened the dynasty",
          "answer": [
            "Yellow Turban Rebellion",
            "Yellow Scarves"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Han established this trade route, named for a natural fiber used to make fine cloth",
          "answer": "Silk Road"
        },
        {
          "question": "Numbered period of civil war that followed the fall of the Han and included clashes between Cao Cao, Sun Jian, and Liu Bei",
          "answer": "Three Kingdoms or Sanguo Shidai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty founded by Wang Mang which temporarily interrupted the Han.",
          "answer": "Xin ] Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pair of Vietnamese sisters who rebelled against the Han Dynasty in 40 CE.",
          "answer": "Trung Sisters or Trung Trac and Trung Nhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Warlord who employed Lu Bu and seized power after deposing Liu Bian",
          "answer": [
            "Dong Zhuo",
            "either",
            "both names",
            "Zhongying 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country held the Nias [[NAI-ahs]] Expedition and fought two wars against the Kingdom of Bone. This country fought the Chinese in Montrado and aided the Adats in the Padri War. This country used the \"Peace Policy\" to take South Sulawesi [[soo-lah-WEH-see]], part of its (20 pts)",
        "Great East governorate. This country fought the Infidel War in Aceh [[AH-cheh]] on Sumatra, and after Prince Diponegoro [[dee-pah- neh-GO-roh]] began a revolt in Selarong, this country fought the Java War in (10 pts)",
        "Batavia. For ten points, name this European country which controlled Indonesia until 1949."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Netherlands",
        "Holland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An artist created a painting during this war depicting a politician bleeding out while being protected by freedman Peter Salem. Artist John Trumbull served in this war, later painting a scene of William Phillips and another general surrendering during this war. (20 pts)",
        "Emanuel Leutze [[LOIT-zuh]] painted multiple scenes of this war, including one where several figures including James (10 pts)",
        "Monroe and Nathaniel Greene traverse a half-frozen river. For ten points, name this war, the setting of Washington Crossing the Delaware."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Revolutionary War",
        "American Revolution"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This man fought the filibusters in the Gutierrez-Magee Expedition and was cited for bravery after the Battle of Medina. With Guadalupe Victoria, this man signed the Plan of Casa Mata to oppose Emperor (*) Augustine's Plan of Iguala. This man traded his highest office with the leader of the puros, Valentin Gomez Farias. James Austin Sylvester captured this man hiding in a marsh after the Battle of (*) San Jacinto. For ten points, name this twelve-time Mexican president who lost the Mexican-American War despite his victory at the Alamo."
      ],
      "answer": "Antonio López de Santa Anna"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This group was founded by William Ireland, Aaron Grosh and Oliver Kelley. Wisconsin passed a strict rate-fixing law based on this group's advocacy called the Potter Law, which stopped all railroad construction in the state. (*) Certain consumers were offered goods through Montgomery Ward, which associated itself with this organization which spurned the Munn v. Illinois decision and created (*) Rural Free Delivery. For ten points, name this fraternal agricultural organization popular after the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Grange",
        "The National Grange of the Order of Patrons of Husbandry 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Possibly as a result of miners finding these objects, Herodotus made the claim that gryphons protected gold mines in Hyperborea. The race between Othniel Charles Marsh and Edward Drinker Cope to collect these objects has been dubbed their (20 pts)",
        "namesake \"war.\" Because he did not believe in extinction, Thomas Jefferson claimed that some of these objects were actually the (10 pts)",
        "remains of an unknown species of elephant. For ten points, name these preserved remains of prehistoric life studied by paleontologists."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Fossils",
        "Bones",
        "Skeletons"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This country sent the Balmis Expedition to vaccinate millions against smallpox. The Duke of Olivares served a king of this nation as did Luis de Haro. This country took Breda in 1624, as shown in Diego (*) Velazquez's The Surrender of Breda, and it signed the Treaty of the Pyrenees to marry Maria Theresa to Louis XIV and end its war with (*) France. The \"Planet King\" of this country patronized authors like Lope de Vega and Calderon de la Barca. For ten points, name this state whose Habsburg rulers included kings named Felipe and Carlos."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Spain",
        "Spanish Empire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Portraits of this artist often feature a broken nose, reflecting an incident in which Pietro Torrigiano [[tohr-EE-jee-AH-noh]] punched him in the face. During Pentecost in 1972, a disturbed geologist named Laszlo Toth vandalized this artist's (*) Pietà. One of this artist's paintings was the subject of the \"fig leaf\" campaign. Due to a mistranslation of the word for \"halo,\" this artist created a sculpture of (*) Moses with two horns. For ten points, name this Italian renaissance artist, who painted The Last Judgement and the Sistine Chapel ceiling."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Michelangelo Buonarroti",
        "Buonarroti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "A company owned by this man inspired the term \"red carpet treatment\" for its treatment of customers. This man's company operated the Water Level Route and the High Line, which is now a park. Grand Central Depot was built by this man for his New York (*) Central Railroad, and this man opposed Daniel Drew's takeover of the Erie Railroad. This man's career began working for steamboat owner Thomas Gibbons of Gibbons v. Ogden fame. The original benefactor to a namesake (*) university in Nashville, for ten points, who was this railroad magnate \"Commodore\"?"
      ],
      "answer": "Cornelius Vanderbilt 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
    }
  ]
}